<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at a visitation in Honiton in Devon, on Wensday in Easter week, 1676 by J.R. Rector of Lezant in Cornwall.</title>
            <author>J. R. (James Rossington), b. 1642 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23078</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12062844</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12062844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 577:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at a visitation in Honiton in Devon, on Wensday in Easter week, 1676 by J.R. Rector of Lezant in Cornwall.</title>
                  <author>J. R. (James Rossington), b. 1642 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Simon Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1676?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, II, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53310:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at a VISITATION In <hi>Honiton</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> On Wenſday in Eaſter Week, 1676.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. R.</hi> Rector of <hi>Lezant</hi> in <hi>Cornwall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Simon Miller</hi> at the Star at the Weſt end of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53310:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53310:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 11.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But if any man ſeems to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle (to ſhew that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quites a <hi>decorum</hi> and decent accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the Act of his worſhip) ſharply inveighs againſt the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> woman, who from a Phantaſtical imitation of the She-Prophets and Prieſts of the Gentiles, (who had their faces diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and their hair diſhevelled, when they uttered their Oracles, or celebrated Rites and ſacrifices to their Gods) at the time of their praying and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying were unveiled in the Church, and appeared bare and open-faced in publick, notwithſtanding it was then accounted an unſeemly and immodeſt guiſe, as he proves it here by ſeveral Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>contrario,</hi> and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. From the decency of this Ceremony of having a veil, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and,</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, From the ſignificancy thereof, <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>So in the 2d. place, from an Argument <hi>ab abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, v.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, He enforced it from the Angelical preſence in the Church, <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly, From an Argument <hi>a pari, v.</hi> 14. <hi>q. d.</hi> how
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53310:3"/>
odd would it be for men to wear a veil, a womans dreſs, ſo by the like reaſon is it as uncomely for women to be without a veil, that is, in the guiſe and dreſs of a man; and however the devils of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſometimes take pleaſure in this unſeemly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrement, in uncomlineſs and abſurd garbs, yet the God whom they worſhip, with the holy Angels who are preſent at their devotions, loves a comely accommodation in ſuch as worſhip him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he concludes from the example and cuſtome both of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, neither of which had any ſuch uſe for their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be unveiled in their ſacred Aſſemblies: <hi>But if any ſeem contentious,</hi> (that is) will not be ſatisfyed with theſe reaſons, let him know that <hi>we,</hi> (that is) we of the circumciſion, <hi>have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God,</hi> (that is) the Chriſtian Churches; ſo St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Anſelm</hi> underſtand it, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Grotius, there is no Canon for it,</hi> nor is it a cuſtome of the Church or Churches of God, <hi>q. d.</hi> If any <hi>adverſus haec,</hi> as the Syriack Tranſlation hath it, againſt all theſe reaſons will contend further, love to argue on, liſt ſtill to ſtrive, as the <hi>Geneva,</hi> here is one reſerves an Argument, which is <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> and ſhould ſilence all further diſputes about it; <hi>we have no Canon nor Conſtitution to warrant it,</hi> neither hath it been <hi>cuſtomarily practiſed in the Churches of God;</hi> nay, we and they have the quite contrary rule and cuſtome, and let this be the final reſolution in the Caſe,</p>
            <p>From the Text then and the context we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the courſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> took to ſatisfy a ſcrupulous conſcience touching a Rite or Ceremony.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53310:3"/>1ſt. He urgeth the reaſonableneſs of the Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if this Method be not effectual, men be not convinced by his reaſons, then he refers them to the Canons and cuſtomes of the Church, from which they are by no means to ſwerve.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear ſome diſaffected and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſpirits (as if they would tax St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf of impertinency) to mutter, ſaying, what means all this ado about a Rite or Ceremony, ſince 'tis of no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matter? it skills not greatly, whether men obſerve it or no, whether covered or bare, ſit or kneel, all's one; but our Apoſtle lets it not go ſo, but judging it a matter of importance, preſſeth the point hard, uſeth ſeveral Arguments, ſpends many verſes, even half a Chapter about it, and as we may ſuppoſe mainly for theſe two reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he diſlikes any contentions at all, ſince in its very nature is included a breach of that peace of which God is, and we ought to be very tender; for if contentions be not taken off at the firſt, within a while, at the 2d. verſe from the text we finde their miſchievous conſequence no leſs then a Schiſme, and the next verſe aſſures us, that they will proceed ſo far as to flat hereſies.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, Becauſe he likes not contentions againſt the Rites and Cuſtomes of the Church, he well knew Satans Methods, this Arch-Antichriſt underſtands, that if he can firſt get himſelf children, they'l at length grow to men; grant him once one ſeemingly modeſt concluſion about a leſſer matter hee'l be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with his bolder Logick to attack greater points: allow him him but the rudeneſs to throw the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice out of the Church, the next news will be, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53310:4"/>
houſe of God is degraded to a ſtable: if [down with the Ceremonies] once become Canonical, 'twill not be long ere the reſpects due to the Sacrament ſhall be little better then Apocryphall; if he may but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the former, you ſhall finde him ſoon after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting of the other, ſo in this Chapter, he falls foul with the Lords Supper; the <hi>Corinthians</hi> firſt <hi>praying in publick, having their heads covered,</hi> and whilſt they approach the Lords throne in ſo uncuſtomary (and therefore irreverent) poſture, can we expect better manners at his Table? accordingly <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they eat and drink there, as if they had been at home, and that ſometimes to exceſs, ſo ill were the effects of a conteſt raiſed at firſt about a circumſtance in the worſhip of God. St. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore oppoſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to theſe practiſes, after other reaſons in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent verſes, he lays for his ground this of the Text. <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtome,</hi>—or more fully according to <hi>Grotius</hi>'s Interpretation, <hi>we have neither Canon</hi> nor <hi>Cuſtome for it;</hi> neither <hi>we, nor the Churches of God;</hi> whence in the firſt place we infer, that as the Churches of God have had, ſo they ſtill have, may, and ought to have, their reſpective canons, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, touching Rites and ceremonies, whereto due obedience ought to be paid by all ſuch as are in communion. This is ſo apparent a truth, that to deny it and judge ſuch Eccleſiaſtical ſanctions and conſtitutions unlawful, is to charge all the ancient known parts of the Church of Chriſt, with a ſinful uſurpation of authority in the Church; for that they enjoyed both in general and provinciall ſynods what thy judged uſeful, is manifeſt, from the canons of the Code of the univerſal Church, and of the <hi>Roman</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53310:4"/>
and <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Churches, and from the more ancient canons amongſt thoſe called the Apoſtles, and from other Eccleſiaſtical rules of diſcipline frequently mentioned in <hi>Tertull. Cyprian</hi> and other ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: <hi>Licet Paſtoribus &amp; Epiſcopis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Art ult. Apol. ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note> &amp;c. it becomes ſuch to make canons that things be done in order in Church, ſo the <hi>Auguſt. Confeſs.</hi> and for the more due and regular obſervance of ſuch Eccleſiaſtical laws, and canons, it hath been the cuſtome of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God, and thoſe too, which we rightly call Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, to require ſubſcriptions thereto; thus it was uſed amongſt the Proteſtants in <hi>Poland,</hi> where,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Falkner</hi> p. 86.</note> after the conſent (chiefly touching the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) was eſtabliſht in the ſynod of <hi>Sandemir Ano. Dni.</hi> 1570. between the Churches of thoſe three confeſſions, the <hi>Bohemian, Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Helvetian,</hi> it was concluded in another following general ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, that none ſhould be admitted into the Miniſtry unleſs <hi>conſenſui ſubſcribat:</hi> the French Church requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red likewiſe a ſubſcription to their Liturgy, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this it hath been the cuſtome even of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, to impoſe ſolemn Oaths for the yet cloſer binding to canonical obedience; thus in the <hi>Behemian</hi> Church, after Ordination the Miniſter was ſolemnly admitted to his Miniſtration by the Viſitours, who among other things committed to him their <hi>liber Ritualis,</hi> containing their form and Rites of worſhip; to the performance thereof, they did oblige themſelves at their Ordination by a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious oath. So at <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> after its firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they who entred into the Miniſtry, did by Oath undertake to keep in the communion and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Church, and its Governours, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53310:5"/>
to the Law of God, and their canons, ſtatutes, and Ordinances: and it is related from the laws of <hi>Geneva</hi> (where an eſtabliſht Liturgy is one of their conſtitutions), that all there who were received to the Miniſtry, muſt oblige themſelves by Oath, to obſerve the Eccleſiaſtical Ordinances ordained by the Councils of that City: and in the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Church, they binde themſelves by oath to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Eccleſiaſtical canons and performing due obedience to the Biſhop: But if the contentious amongſt us will condemn all Eccleſiaſtical laws and ſanctions, and account nothing pure, but what is uſed in their conventicles, I dare joyn iſſue with them even upon that, and appeal to their own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and preſcriptions, whether many things are not ordered according to the humours of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; beſides men are very much miſtaken to think ceremonies and conſtitutions meerly indifferent, I mean, in the general; for however every particular ceremony be indifferent, and every particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is arbitrary, and alterable, yet that there ſhould be ſome ceremonies it is neceſſary; <hi>neceſſitate abſolutâ,</hi> inſomuch as no outward work can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without ceremonious circumſtances, ſome or other; and that there ſhould be ſome conſtitutions concerning them, it is alſo neceſſary, though not ſimply and abſolutely, as the former, yet <hi>ex hypotheſi, &amp; neceſſitate convenientiae,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>quot capita, tot ſchiſmata;</hi> whereof what other would be the iſſue but infinite diſtractions, and diſorderly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions in the Church, when every one acts as his humour leads him, and that upon this account Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions ſome or other are neceſſary, is agreeable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53310:5"/>
to the Apoſtles when they met in a Council at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> for ſetling the Churches peace; We reade, <hi>Acts.</hi> 15.28. that they would lay no other burthen <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beſides theſe neceſſary things: 'twas not enough with them, that the things would be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary when they had required them, but they looked on an antecedent neceſſity, which was the only ground of their impoſing theſe Commands upon the Gentile-Chriſtians: but obſerve, this antecedent neceſſity did not ariſe from the nature of the things enjoyned, but from the expediency and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy there was for the Injunction, by reaſon of the preſent juncture of affairs, and to ſay otherwiſe, would be to contradict the Apoſtle, or make him to contradict himſelf: from which Apoſtolical fynod (as may be well noted) the <hi>London</hi>-Miniſters in their <hi>Jusdivinum</hi> allow a Synod power of impoſing things on the Church, which they aſſert to be included in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and conſequently, that things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in their own nature become neceſſary to be practiced after ſuch a decree or Injunction,<note place="margin">Cap. 13.</note> the like do the Aſſembly grant in their Confeſſion; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Apoſtles did not only exerciſe this power when they ſat in Council together, but when they were aſunder alſo: St. <hi>Paul</hi> often mentions Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions that he made for diverſe Churches, for the Church of <hi>Galatia</hi> he made an Order,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1.2.</note> that Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the poor ſhould be made on every firſt day of the week,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> and meant to bring in the ſame cuſtome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church: he framed Ordinances al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that Church:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 3.14.</note> ſo for the Church of <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> where he commanded oppoſers againſt his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations to be excommunicated; neither could
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53310:6"/>
ſuch things as theſe be commanded by an unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able law, ſince they are to be taken up and laid aſide, as occaſion ſerveth, therefore the Apoſtle having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in matters of faith and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, puts off theſe other matters till his own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he might ſee what is moſt expedient; <hi>the reſt will I ſet in order when I come,</hi> where he promiſeth you ſee to appoint things belonging to outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; now we know, that he never came to <hi>Corinth</hi> after that, who then did order thoſe other things, but the Governours of the Church? he might have preſcribed unto them a compleat form for outward Order and Polity, but he foreſaw that the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders would not ſuit every ſtate of a particular Church, and therefore his coming being prevented, his ſucceſſours had power to determine of things; and if the ſame orders and conſtitutions will not ſerve a particular Church at all times, how was it poſſible for the Apoſtles to expreſs all matters of Rites and Orders belonging to the Catholick Church? ſometimes the Church hath to do with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, ſometimes with Hereticks, and thoſe diverſe, by reaſon whereof the Church hath been occaſioned to change her Rites, as namely dipping in baptiſme, which ſhe hath changed from thrice to once, and from once to thrice; accordingly as the 20th Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle aſcribes a power to the Church to decree Rites and Ceremonies, ſo the 34th ſays, every particular Church hath authority to ordain, change or aboliſh Ceremonies or Rites in the Church: the ſame in the Articles of Religion of the Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> printed in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> and accords with the Confeſſion of the Reformed Church of <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53310:6"/>
publiſhed in the year 1562. which adds,<note place="margin">Diſcipl. des Egl. Reform. de Franc. Ch. des Conſiſtoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Art. <hi>31. as may be ſeen alſo in</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. Eccl. Gal. inter opuſcula Calvini.</note> 
               <hi>qui hoc de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trectant cerebroſi &amp; pervicaces apud nos habentur,</hi> ſuch as refuſe to obey are accounted with us obſtinate and brainſick; and accordingly ought they to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt; and in caſe other Methods do not take, <hi>ils ſeront retrenches de l' Egliſe,</hi> they are to be out off from the Church: ſo our Saviour, <hi>he that heareth not the Church, let him be unto thee, as a heathen man and a publican,</hi> and what is the condition of ſuch? <hi>they are delivered over unto Satan;</hi> a ſad condition, if true, and moſt true it is, <hi>verily I ſay unto you, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye ſhall binde on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven;</hi> this is no <hi>brutum fulmen:</hi> ſuch a blinding as this, may be a prologue to the caſting into utter darkneſs: <hi>hoc vero erat futuri judicii praejudicium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> this doom is the forerunner of the day of doom, and a true preſident of that ſentence, which ſhall then paſs upon diſobedient perſons, which hath been ſo deeply reſented by ſome, that we reade of many in Hiſtory, who would not admit of comfort after Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, till they were reconciled to the Church; and if I miſtake not, the inceſtuous perſon men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. may be a pregnant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, after whoſe excommunication, ſo deep a ſorrow ſeiſed upon him, as that the Apoſtle himſelf fearing that he ſhould be ſwallowed up with it, for the ſaving of his ſoul, gave order for his abſolution: ſuch then, as will not obey the conſtitutions of the Church, muſt look to feel the weight of her cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: but if after this any perſevere in their perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then the Magiſtrate may doubtleſs by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, uſed with Chriſtian moderation, endeavour to ſtop the ſpreading of the contagion, and do what in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53310:7"/>
wiſdome he thinks meet to preſerve the purity and peace of Church and State, urging againſt them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. or 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. or that of <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12. <hi>I would that they were even cut off that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you;</hi> whereby doubtleſs is meant, not a cutting off from the Church by way of Excommunication, for that was in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> power to do, nay, they had cut themſelves off from the Church before, but a cutting off by the civil power which then was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and therefore he would not have it made uſe of by Chriſtians, for he would not allow them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to unbelieving Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1.</note> no, not in Civil, much leſs in Spiritual matters; and ſo wiſheth only there were a fitting power, that is, a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to puniſh or baniſh thoſe that trouble the Church of Chriſt, or ſince there was no ſuch power, he inprecates, that God would be pleaſed to cut them off by his own hand: and in the Apoſtles time 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervable, that there were corporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments miraculouſly added to the Churches cenſures, upon the obſtinate and contumacious; not only in the particular Inſtances of <hi>Saul, Ananias, Saphira, Elimas,</hi> but the delivering a perſon unto Satan, hath been ordinarily obſerved, to include with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Church, a giving him over to ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bodily calamities, to be inflicted on him by the evil ſpirit; of which a particular inſtance is given by <hi>Paulinus</hi> in the life of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prope finem.</note> concerning the ſervant of one <hi>Stilico:</hi> and this is preſumed to have continued in the Church, whilſt it ſubſiſted without any influence from the ſecular power, but when once the Church came to be incorporated into the Common-wealth, the miraculous way of adding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53310:7"/>
puniſhment to the Churches cenſures ceaſed, and the Magiſtrate took care to enforce the ſpiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the Church with the more ſenſibly keen and ſharp ones of the Civil State. Thus is it done at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> it ſelf; where the Magiſtrates ſhew great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour againſt them that are diſobedient to the Orders of the Church; inſomuch that if any be ſo unwiſe as to diſpiſe them, he is openly puniſhed with Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or otherwiſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. l.</hi> p. 311.</note> 
               <hi>Si quis praefract auctoritatem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaeſpernat,</hi>—If any one (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) do obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ſlight the authority of the Church, unleſs he leaves his contumacy, he is baniſhed by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for a year, and if any one ſhew himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly and ſtubborn, the Senate doth take the cauſe to it ſelf, and puniſheth the Party: ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders therefore, as diſobey the Orders and Canons of the Church, and contumaciouſly perſiſt therein, ought to be ſoundly ſcourged by the Paſtoral rod, and cut off from the body of the Church by the ſpiritual ſword of excommunication; and if that will not work a reformation, as indeed it is not likely to do, upon the more obſtinate and ſchiſmatical, who are like to think themſelves ſhrewdly hurt, by being cut off from that body, which they chuſe not to be of and ſo being puniſhed into a quiet enjoyment of their ſweet ſeparation, they have but their deſerts; if, as examples and warning to others, they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up into the hands of the civil powers, and ſo they be haled to the Judge, and the Judge deliver them to the Officer, and the Officer caſt them into Priſon: indeed were the Conſciences of men as they ſhould be, the cenſures of the Church might be a ſufficient coertion upon them, but being as too
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53310:8"/>
many are, hell and damnation-proof, if the Biſhop had no other defenſives but Excommunication, no other power but that of the keys, he may (as one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) for any notable effect, he is like to do upon the factious and contumacious, ſurrender his Paſtoral ſtaff, ſhut up the Church; and put thoſe keys under the door; Thus then we have ſeen that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God have, may, and ought to have, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their Canons and Conſtitutions, to which all Chriſtians are bound to give obedience, otherwiſe they incur the Churches cenſures, and are worthy to be debarred the priviledge of ſuch a ſociety, and what other puniſhment the Civil Magiſtrate thinks good to annex.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, We infer, that the Church hath her cuſtomes: now in caſe there be no certain conſtitution, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral received cuſtome hath the force of a law; thus all Societies, beſides their laws in books, have their cuſtomes in practice,<note place="margin">Pand. <hi>1</hi> Tit. <hi>3.</hi> de legibus. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> and thoſe not to be taken up and laid down at every mans pleaſure: the Civil-Law ſays this of cuſtome, <hi>Imo magnae Authoritatis hoc jus habetur ut non fuerit ſcripto comprehendere neceſſe;</hi> ſo the Apoſtle here was zealous for Church-cuſtomes, as were likewiſe all the Fathers of the Nicene Council, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let cuſtomes ſay they prevail, let them carry it: and in thoſe things (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) wherein the holy Scripture hath defined nothing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 85.</note> 
               <hi>mos populi Dei &amp; inſtituta majorum pro lege tenenda ſunt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus hoc egiſſe videtur ut ad recept pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias axioma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vel formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las reſpiceret, <hi>Heinſius.</hi>
               </note> the cuſtomes of Gods people and the appointments of our forefathers muſt be held for laws, but we need no other, and can have no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtance in this caſe, then our Saviour himſelf, who, when he came into the world, complyed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53310:8"/>
with the Rites and cuſtomes he found, and this is the Topick whence our Apoſtle deduceth the laſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument he here uſeth in a matter of decency: 'tis in a word, <hi>'tis not the cuſtome:</hi> which alone ought to ſuffice in things of that nature, though no other could be alledged, and which indeed ought to be alledged alone without any more ado, when we have to deal with contentious perſons St. <hi>Paul</hi> we finde was content to reaſon with thoſe as were capable of ſatisfaction, but for ſuch whom no reaſon could ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy, but would be always contradicting and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring, he thought them not worthy of any other anſwer, then telling them, ſuch is not, or ſuch is the cuſtome received and practized in the Church of God. Now againſt ſuch contentious ſpirits amongſt us, I ſhall make the ſame plea, and in juſtification of the known Rites and ceremonies and conſtitutions of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> appeal to the the ancient uſages and cuſtoms of other Churches; I'le in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt, That of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> we reade of white veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> and St. <hi>Jeroms</hi> time; <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, Virgil,</hi> and <hi>Iſidore</hi> write, it was ordained by <hi>Stephanus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in the third Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, to be uſed by Miniſters on their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; he that reads the 41 Chapter of the 4th Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> will finde, that it was uſed at that time; and <hi>Theodoret</hi> tells us that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> gave one to <hi>Macarius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> as a peculiar garment to miniſter in: and the Etymology of the word <hi>Superpelliceum</hi> uſed to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify a <hi>Surplice,</hi> denotes it to be of ancient uſe: and 'tis well obſerved, that in the Arabick language,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53310:9"/>
the Apoſtles in oppoſition to the <hi>Chemarims</hi> (which <hi>Junius</hi> renders <hi>Atratos</hi>) are termed by a word which ſome render <hi>Albicantes,</hi> others <hi>viri albis induti veſtibus,</hi> men in white veſts or Surplices, as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by <hi>Buxtorfius,</hi> and hath been obſerved by R. D. <hi>Kimchi</hi> on <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4. The Votaries likewiſe of the Lamb of God are repreſented to St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. D. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 198 and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion by ſeveral other Reformed Churches. <hi>vid. Conſenſ. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domir.</hi>
               </note> as celebrating his ſolemn ſervice in the Chriſtian Church in this habit. Moreover the Surplice is at this day uſed in the Reformed Churches of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> confeſſion: and whence is our <hi>Dominica in albis,</hi> our Whit-ſunday, but from the white Robes then worn by all Chriſtians; and if ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſed it then, may not one in a congregation uſe it now.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Juſt. Martyr <hi>againſt</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. <hi>and in his 2d. Apol.</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. de Coron. Mil. &amp; de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. <hi>St.</hi> Cypr. de lapſis &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>56.</hi> ad Thib. <hi>S.</hi> Auſt. Tom. <hi>8. p. 262.</hi>
               </note>2dly. <hi>The Croſs,</hi> it was oft times uſed by all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Primitive times, and particularly in the Office for <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> as <hi>Tertull.</hi> and others witneſs; and ſo the Reformed Churches of the confeſſion of <hi>Augsburgh</hi> for the moſt part uſe it, and in other parts of Divine Service; and for further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that 'tis according to ancient cuſtome, I refer you to the 18 Cannon: nor can it be ſaid to be an addition to the Sacrament of Baptiſme, as the Rubrick before private Baptiſme declares, nor a diſtinct Sacrament, having no inviſible grace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying it, which is eſſentiall to conſtitute a Sacrament, neither do we pretend it hath; ſo that 'tis not unlawful upon either of thoſe Accounts, its uſe being (as the words which are ſpoken at the making of it expreſly declare) only to ſignify, as among the Primitive Chriſtians; as when the King having created thoſe noble knights of his Order,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53310:9"/>
beſtows upon them the Garter, and the blew Riband, as badges to be known by of others, and to put them in minde of the great honour done unto them; in like manner when the Infant hath by baptiſme been inrolled in the Militia of the king of glory, this ſigne of the Croſs is made upon his forehead, to declare that he was conſecrated to Chriſt crucifyed, that he hath put on his Livery, and wears his Badge.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. <hi>The Ring in Marriage:</hi> by a large conſent of Churches and Nations hath a Ring been thought fit to eſtabliſh the Matrimoniall contract, as a pledge or earneſt thereof; whence 'twas the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary cuſtome of the Jews to uſe the Ring of eſpouſing, as <hi>Buxtorf.</hi> witneſſeth: the like among the cuſtomes of the Romans;<note place="margin">Juvenal.</note> 
               <hi>Et digitis pignus fortaſſe dediſti:</hi> but yet notwithſtanding no part of their paganiſme; as <hi>Tertul.</hi> evinceth; <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> calls it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Idol.</hi> c. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Arram ſponſi:</hi> In the Reformed Church of <hi>Heſſen</hi> they marry with a Ring, they do the like in <hi>Lithuania,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. The <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> and our often repeating of it: the Jews ordinarily uſed ſome ſuch doxology or <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> and the Non-conformiſts at this day at the end of their prayers four or five times in an Aſſembly uſe that doxology, to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Arabick verſion of the Pſalms we have, Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the end of every tenth Pſalm, and was probably in practice at the end of every Pſalm. If being reaſonably ſuppoſed that the words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, ought to excite and ſtir up all the faithful who heard them recited, to praiſe the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53310:10"/>
Lord and magnify his Name. <hi>Damaſus</hi> appointed it to be ſo in the 4th. Century,<note place="margin">Caſs. <hi>l. 2.</hi> de Inſtit. Caenob.</note> who was then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the Weſtern Churches uſed it ſo, we have the teſtimony of <hi>Caſſianus,</hi> who lived above 1300 years ago,<note place="margin">When we aſſert any thing with much earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſay, this is the truth, and we will ſtand to it. Biſhop <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
               </note> and moreover he witneſſeth, that in all the Churches of <hi>France</hi> they uſed to ſtand at it, and ſurely if we may and ought to ſtand at the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the Apoſtles Creed, to ſhew our conſtancy and readineſs to maintain that faith which we there profeſs, much more at this Hymn, which is both a <hi>Compendium</hi> or ſhort profeſſion of our faith, and a ſong of praiſe to God.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly, <hi>Standing at the Goſpel;</hi> this is likewiſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient, as appears by the Decree made for that purpoſe by <hi>Anaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 400. mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Platina</hi> in his life; and if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Durantus,</hi> it was in uſe long before.</p>
            <p n="6">6ly, <hi>Standing at the Pſalms and Hymns;</hi> this geſture is taken notice of in Scripture as very proper for our lands and thankſgivings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.2.135 1, 2.</note> at this Office we reade all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood in <hi>Davids</hi> time, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. and ſo long after the Levites called to the people <hi>to ſtand up and bleſſe the Lord their God, Neh.</hi> 9.5.</p>
            <p n="7">7ly, <hi>Kneeling at the receiving of the Euchariſt;</hi> this hath been anciently uſed in the Church, and the more generally obſerved by reaſon of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who denyed the deity of Chriſt; ſo ought it to be uſed againſt the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereticks and Familiſts; and if you will in oppoſition to the Pope, who all inſolently ſhew their equality with Chriſt himſelf, by receiving it ſitting, a geſture which at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Communion hath been prohibited, if not condemned, by a full Synod of Proteſtants
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53310:10"/>
in <hi>Poland:</hi> moreover it was the ordinary geſture in the Romiſh Pagan Idolatry, the ancient laws of their Pagan-worſhip requiring, <hi>Ut adoraturiſedeant,</hi> which as <hi>Plutarch</hi> affirmeth, was appointed by <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pompilius:</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> informs us, that at their Gentile Solemnities, even in his time <hi>adoratis ſigillaribas ſuis ſedendo.</hi> And beſides ſitting at prayers (when I hope we are lifting up our hearts as we receive the Sacrament) is againſt all Scripture.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Et procumben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus interim in genua di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribuunt, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. <hi>Confeſ. Art. 13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Denique ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra Synaxi Corpus &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſimul percipientes iis Ceremon. quas Eccleſia Crac vienſis in uſu habet, <hi>who were ſuch as joyned themſelves with the</hi> fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres Bohemi, vid. <hi>at the end of the Acts of the General Aſſembly of</hi> Cracovia.</p>
                  <p>Anno <hi>1573.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Preſidents and Commands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6. and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18. is rather to be rendred, <hi>he ſtood before the Lord and ſaid,</hi> and <hi>Vatablus</hi> well obſerves upon it, <hi>non licuit ſedentem orare,</hi> ſo in the N. T. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.36, 21, 5, 9, 40. This was forbidden in the primitive Church, as <hi>Tertull.</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>ſedentem orare extra diſciplinam,</hi> to ſit at prayers is againſt the rules of worſhip: he that miniſtreth may ſometimes kneel, ſometimes ſtand, but he hath no warrant to ſet when he prayeth: thus <hi>Solomon</hi> at the Dedication of the Temple immediatly after one prayer upon his knees, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.54. he beginneth another of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ſtanding, <hi>v.</hi> 56.57. but what geſture more convenient for the devout receiver then this of kneeling, who as he kneels may abaſe himſelf to the duſt, and again (with the Royal Votary) may lift up his hands to God, and may look up.</p>
            <p n="8">8ly, <hi>Bowing at the name of Jeſus;</hi> for this I refer you to the 18th Canon, and 52. Injunction of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to certify you, that it hath been an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome of the Church; neither can any more be reaſonably objected againſt it then going to Church at the toll of the Bell; for as the one tells us the time when we are to worſhip God, ſo the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53310:11"/>
of the name of Jeſus puts us only in minde of him we owe all reverence to, without diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him as the object of our worſhip by any Image of him, which only repreſents that which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the object nor reaſon of our worſhip. In <hi>Spain</hi> 'tis the cuſtome as oft as they make mention of their King, they uncover their head, adding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all this ſhort Salutation, <hi>Nueſtro ſenior que dios guarde muchos anios,</hi> our Lord whom God preſerve many years:<note place="margin">In the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>Lithua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Polonia,</hi> and <hi>Bremen,</hi> where they have their hats on at Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways put them off at the name of <hi>Jeſus, vid Durel.</hi> p. 34.</note> So Embaſſadors at their ſolemn Audience being covered, yet to ſhew their great reverence to their King whom they repreſent, they uncover their heads as oft as they make mention of him; how much more reaſon have we who profeſs to be Chriſtians, at our ſolemn Audiences and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, to uſe ſome token of Reverence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to the King of Kings, our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as oft as we hear him mentioned: the truth is, all the names of God are holy, yet becauſe the name <hi>Jeſus</hi> exhibites to us the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of God in the moſt endearing circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, therefore as the Myſteries celebrated on the Altar cauſed that preference of it before all other parts of the Church, for to do our worſhip towards, (which is to be our next inſtance) ſo this name of Jeſus above all other names or words that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify God or his attributes, may well be made uſe of to determine the time and occaſion, when in the time of Divine Service we ſhould more exuberantly venture devotion in the worſhipping God our Saviour, eſpecially the Scripture ſeeming to hint ſome ſuch thing to us.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53310:11"/>9ly, <hi>Bowing towards the Altar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>When ye enter into an houſe Salute it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Matt. 10. and why ſhould we not think it a part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious manners to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, when we come into the houſe of God. <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.6. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.29</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>or at our entring in and going out of the Church;</hi> which though not enjoyned by Canon, but left <hi>ad libitum,</hi> is yet ſo far recommended to us as an ancient cuſtome, as ought at leaſt to put to ſilence ſuch as are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and quarrelſome, againſt thoſe that obſerve it: we reade that <hi>Moſes</hi> did reverence at the very door of the Tabernacle, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20. and that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> and all that were preſent with him, when they had made an end of offering, <hi>bowed and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped:</hi> and for our bowing at our nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the holy table, or the Altar, practiſed by Qu. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> and which all the honourable Knights of the Garter are bound to by their Order, it is of the ſame nature with putting off our hats whilſt we are in the Church, and only determines a natural Act of reverence that way, which the Primitive Chriſtians did uſe, to direct their worſhip and Adoration; being an Act of addreſs, and of tender of honour unto God; 'tis therefore moſt fitly to be performed at or towards the place of our addreſs, <hi>viz.</hi> the Altar, whereat anciently, as the Euchariſt, ſo the whole devotions of the Church were performed, and preſented to the divine Majeſty; from which ſpiritual Sacrifices it received the name; ſo that all the honour the Altar receives in theſe adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made towards it, is this,<note place="margin">D. Moore.</note> that it is uſed as a directive Inſtrument for people to ſhew which way they are to ſet their faces when they make theſe adorations to God, but the worſhip is no more done to the Altar by being done towards it, then it is done to the Church by being done in it.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53310:12"/>10ly, <hi>Turning and praying towards the Eaſt:</hi> this hath been anciently commanded by <hi>Vigilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Sanct.</hi> l. 3. l. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Auno Chriſti,</hi> 540. and ſome write, that it was a tradition from the Apoſtles in ſolemn and publick prayers in the Church,<note place="margin">Damaſcene.</note> that all ſhould turn their faces towards the Eaſt, and for that reaſon Churches were built Eaſtwards,<note place="margin">Greg. <hi>in his</hi> Critic. Notes.</note> and a Canon to this purpoſe is aſcribed to their name in the Arabick Code, to which agrees alſo an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient profeſſion of the Eaſtern Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſays, this was the cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: ſo St. <hi>Auſt.</hi> and he gives this as a reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Eaſt is the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable part of the world being the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of light whence the glorious Sun ariſeth, <hi>Auſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Serm. Dom. in mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. c.</hi> 5.</note> to be ſeen in the learned <hi>Gregories</hi> Notes; and to make the cuſtome to be of the greateſt antiquity, the ſame Author obſerves, that the Eaſt in the Hebrew tongue is called <hi>Redem,</hi> the face or forepart; the Weſt <hi>Achor,</hi> the back-part; the North <hi>Smol,</hi> the left hand; the South <hi>Teman,</hi> the right hand; which impoſitions (ſays he) reſpected either the making the firſt man towards the Eaſt, or rather the religious poſture at that time; and that <hi>Adam</hi> called the North the left hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſervice of God turned his face towards the Eaſt; and there is great probability that he was no ſooner diſpatch't out of the duſt, but he fell down to the ſame earth again, and adored his Maſter this ſame way: and 'tis not to be omitted, that our bleſſed Saviour is called the Eaſt, and that <hi>his ſtar appeared in the Eaſt,</hi> and the Wiſe men came from thence; nay more, the Angels that proclaimed his Nativity, for their Temple is to be ſeen upon the Eaſt of <hi>Bethlem;</hi> he was born too in the Eaſtern parts of the world, nay, <hi>in orientati angulo Civitatis Bethlem,</hi> ſays <hi>Bede:</hi> but that he aſcended up in the Eaſtern part of the heavens, it hath had the moſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53310:12"/>
ancient and full conſent of the whole Church; and if he ſo aſcended, we need not doubt but he'l return by the ſame way that he went: the Angels intimate as much, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.27. accordingly we lay in our dead with their faces towards the Eaſt, as if they ſhould ſtand and riſe upon their feet (at the Reſurrection) to meet the Lord in the Eaſt: well therefore may we have reſpect to that rather then any other Region of heaven in our ſolemn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions.</p>
            <p n="11">11ly, <hi>Reading and Singing the Pſalms and Hymns</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternately; this agrees with the ancient practice of the Greek and Latin Churches; ſo <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> teſtify, and St. <hi>Baſil</hi> having brought it into his Church of <hi>Neo-Caeſarea</hi> to avoid any thoughts of ſingularity and novelty pleads for his warrant,<note place="margin">Baſil. ad Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Churches of <hi>Aegypt, Theſſolonica, Libia, Paleſtine,</hi> the <hi>Arabians, Phenic. Syrians, Meſop.</hi> among whom the cuſtome was. Of <hi>Anna</hi> 'tis recorded, that ſhe did anſwer in her gratulatory confeſſion to <hi>Simeon,</hi> that went before her therein, as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> renders the original: That this was the practice in the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> founded by St. <hi>Mark,</hi> we have likewiſe the report of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> out of <hi>Philo Judaeus;</hi> and the ſame <hi>Philo Jud.</hi> averreth, that that ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the children of <hi>Iſrael, Exodus</hi> 5.1, 20. was uttered with reſponſal melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, alternately repeated, and both the <hi>Joma</hi> and other tracts of the <hi>Talmud</hi> mention the people in the period of their prayers, expreſſing, <hi>Bleſſed be the name of the glory of his Kingdome for ever and ever. Ignatius</hi> goes further, and tells us, that this is the pattern ſet us by the Quire of Angels, who cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53310:13"/>
one to another, the Seraphim to the Cherubim, and the Cherubim ecchoing back again to the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 6.2.</note> 
               <note place="margin">The reformed Churches of <hi>Heſſen</hi> and <hi>Bremen</hi> uſe to ſing their Pſalms and Hymns by courſe, <hi>vid. Durel.</hi> p 38.</note> 
               <hi>holy, holy, holy:</hi> and <hi>Pliny</hi> writing to <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> in the Chriſtians behalf, in the firſt Century, ſaid, they uſed to ſing and praiſe Chriſt <hi>ſecum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicem:</hi> and what exerciſe more becoming Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Aſſemblies, then thus in his Temple to be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſpeaking of his honour, and praiſing of him: The manner of performance could not be more decently and to greater Edification provided for, then is preſcribed by Canon or Cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, were our hearts but once in tune for ſo ſacred a work, and our practice more uniform, devout and harmonious in the Celebration of it: In a word, what can more fitly declare our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing one another, then the rehearſal of theſe Pſalms and Hymns interchangeably and by courſe together, and that we do all this with grace or gratitude in our hearts unto the Lord, then the Doxology added in the concluſion.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Epiſt. ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 1.2.</note>12ly, <hi>The Liturgy it ſelf,</hi> as 'tis a ſet and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed form; 'tis well noted on <hi>Timothy</hi> the firſt Chapt. of the firſt Epiſtle, that that place hath a particular reference of this duty of prayer to the publick ſervice of God, which will appear very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, if we conſider, that the Epiſtle is an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to <hi>Timothy</hi> who was inveſted with Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Authority by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore ought to take care that common Supplications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be made in the publick Aſſemblies; to this purpoſe is that Gloſs of <hi>Beza</hi> on the words following: <hi>I will that men pray every where, &amp;c. omnem locum intellige ſacris caetibus deſtinatum,</hi> and more fully that of <hi>Aretius,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53310:13"/>
who ſaith, that as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had given <hi>Timothy</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the former Chapter, to take care that ſound Doctrine were preached to the people, ſo here, <hi>ut certam habeant formulam,</hi> a certain form of prayer conſiſting of thoſe ſeveral parts there enumerated: in purſuance of this Apoſtolical Exhortation the Churches have ſtill had their Liturgies, and that repleniſhed with this variety. The <hi>Indians</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> have their ſervice in the Syriack tongue, and their Liturgy is tranſlated thence into Latine, and to be ſeen in <hi>Bibliotheca veterum Patrum,</hi> ſo is the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy of the <hi>Cophti</hi> or Chriſtians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> made by <hi>Severus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> and there is alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother attributed to St. <hi>Peter</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Lindanus:</hi> The Aethiopian Liturgy which hath St. <hi>Matthew</hi> for its reputed Author,<note place="margin">The Liturgy of St. <hi>James</hi> beginneth thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>vid. Chriſtianogr.</hi> p. 96. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. p. 28.</note> ſet down by <hi>Francis Alvarez</hi> in the Portugal tongue, and afterwards written in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, is mentioned by <hi>Caſſand.</hi> in his Liturgies: <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſippus</hi> noteth, that St. <hi>James</hi> was called <hi>Jacobus Liturgicus</hi> for a form of ſervice compoſed by him for the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whereof he was Biſhop, it is printed in Greek and Latine; there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Liturgies aſcribed to St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> or <hi>Greg. Nazianz</hi> uſed in the Greek Church, and one of St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of which he gives a large account in his Catechiſm. The <hi>Gregorian</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Liturgy, the <hi>Muſarabick</hi> Liturgy of <hi>Spain</hi> compoſed by <hi>Iſidore Hiſpalen.</hi> the <hi>Officium Ambroſianum,</hi> and that of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuinus</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which <hi>Bede</hi> mentions, together with the <hi>Dutch, Suevick, French</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies: that of <hi>Geneva</hi> to be ſeen in <hi>French, Latine</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſet forth by <hi>Calvin;</hi> that of <hi>Scotland</hi> compiled by <hi>Knoks;</hi> and if theſe be not inſtances e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53310:14"/>
for this cuſtome, Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> will aſſure you, that all the Churches in the Chriſtian world in the firſt and beſt times, had their ſet forms of Liturgy: and though it be ſuppoſed, that ſome of thoſe which are extant are not genuine, yet the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church where they are uſed, is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of great authority to any prudent man, if not that theſe Liturgies are purely the ſame with thoſe that were written by thoſe holy men, yet that there were ſuch Liturgies of their penning:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.6, 7.</note> moreover have we not a ſet form of worſhip and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs unto God recorded by St. <hi>John,</hi> as ſung in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, compoſed out of the ſongs of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> which certainly is a very good Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for us, although but revealed to St. <hi>John</hi> by way of viſion and extaſy: or if you look back to the times before the Goſpel, nay, before the Law, the Jews have a form of prayer recorded which they ſay was uſed by <hi>Noah,</hi> you may ſee it in the original; in the Notes of that learned <hi>Gregory,</hi> many of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms were uſed, as the Jewiſh Liturgy; and the profound <hi>Mede</hi> gives them that Title; one notable Inſtance there is for the antiquity of forms of publick and preſcribed prayers, in a Samaritan Chronicle or record, which the renowned Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh</hi> procured from the Library of the learned <hi>Joſeph Scaliger:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spicilegium,</hi> p. 68.</note> more you may obſerve in the Rabbins works, and from them in <hi>Scaliger, Selden, Fagins, Buxtorfius,</hi> and <hi>Capellus</hi> tells us with <hi>Selden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his Notes on <hi>Eutich.</hi> p. 42. 411.</note> that <hi>Ezra</hi> and his houſe the great Synagogue, appointed 18 Forms of Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: the <hi>Jewiſh Talmud,</hi> eſpecially that part called the <hi>Miſchna</hi> is full of ſuch forms, which carry the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53310:14"/>
names of the ancient Rabbins that compoſed them: the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Talmud</hi> is entituled (as <hi>Buxtorf</hi> obſerves) <hi>Berachos,</hi> i. e. of bleſſings and prayers for the fruit of the earth; and the practiſe of the Jews ever ſince the penning of the <hi>Talmud</hi> in recording their ſet forms of prayer upon diverſe occaſions, is an Argument that it was their uſe to compoſe ſuch, and uſe them in more ancient times, as is evident by the many volumes of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick devotions publiſhed by them: the Aſſembly appointed a form of prayer for the Navy, from which they were not to vary, and <hi>Smectimnuus</hi> allowed of impoſition in ſome caſes: for they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this as an expedient, if it ſhall appear any Miniſter proves inſufficient, to diſcharge the duty of prayer in a conceived way, it may be impoſed upon him as a puniſhment to uſe a ſet form and no other; but what would they have done if the perſon thought himſelf ſufficient: Further, that the Lords prayer was preſcribed as a form is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe acknowledged by the Aſſembly in their Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations on that place of St. <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> l. 3. <hi>contr. Pelagianos. Auſtin. Epiſt.</hi> 59. <hi>Greg.</hi> l. 7. Ep. 63. <hi>Ambr.</hi> l. 5. <hi>de Sacra.</hi> c. 4.</note> and accordingly hath it been made uſe of in the Church of God; St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, it was uſed in all the Chriſtian world, and generally uſed in all Liturgies and publick prayers and adminiſtration of the Lords Supper: ſo St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Gregory the great,</hi> ſaith, it was uſed by the Apoſtles: <hi>Fox</hi> grants as much in his diſputation about the Maſs, and the ſame <hi>Gregory</hi> noteth moreover, that in the Greek Church it was ordinarily ſaid by all the people together:<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Corpus diſcipl.</hi> of the Dutch Church of <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> the Church of <hi>France</hi> and other Reformed Churches do repeat it ſeveral times
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53310:15"/>
in their Liturgies, and ſuch Proteſtants as follow the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Confeſſion, and thoſe of the Reformed Church of <hi>Holland</hi> ſay it ordinarily before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meals at the end of their Graces:<note place="margin">Euſch. delaud. Conſtant. &amp; de vit. Conſt. <hi>l. 4. c. 19. 20.</hi> Ibid. <hi>c. 17.</hi>
               </note> to add further, it is not probable that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour would have compoſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, godly prayers for the uſe of his ſouldiers, if ſuch forms had not then been uſed in the Chriſtian Church, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports he did; and the ſame Author ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, prayers that were conſtituted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: <hi>Origen</hi> a 100 years before cites a piece of the uſual Liturgy, ſaying, <hi>frequenter in oratione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus da omnipotens, da nobis partem cum prophetis,</hi> &amp;c. and in his book againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. 23. Canon of the 3d Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carth. Anno Chriſti</hi> 317. the reaſon which the Council adds is, <hi>ne forte ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que contra fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vel per ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiam vel per minus ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium ſit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> the very ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> gives for the Jewiſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy from <hi>Ezra's</hi> time in his Notes on <hi>Eutich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vid. D. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds Collect.</hi> from hence, in his view of the Directory. <hi>Sect.</hi> 15.</p>
               </note> he declares Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to uſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> prayers which were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained or conſtituted: St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> intimates uſe of forms in the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> ſervice, by deſcribing the entrance <hi>ſurſum corda,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Tertullian</hi> a form of abrenunciation in baptiſm: <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> hath the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Common-prayer; and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Laodicea</hi> ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Liturgy of prayers; and the 18th Canon thereof is, that none ſhould pray <hi>arbitrio,</hi> but <hi>ſemper eaedem preces.</hi> The Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> ordained thus: <hi>Quicunque preces aliunde deſumit,</hi> &amp;c. whoſoever ſhould frame any other prayers, ſhould firſt conſult with his more learned Brethren, thinking it fit, that in this part of Gods worſhip, eſpecially the Spirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſhould be ſubject to the Prophets: thence we have <hi>Calvins Valde probo,</hi> ſpeaking of a form of prayer, in his Epiſtle to the Protector: <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Magneſians</hi> doth earneſtly enjoyn, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that there be one Common prayer in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53310:15"/>
all the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mileb.</hi> Can. 12</note> and in proceſs of time the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitan</hi> Council did accordingly take care, that the prayers of the Church, and no others ſhould be uſed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canon.</hi> 5. <hi>Anno.</hi> 324.</note> and the Council of <hi>Gangrene</hi> hath made one Canon to this end, <hi>ne orationes Eccleſiae contemnantur:</hi> yet this I muſt needs ſay, we are not ſo reſtrained, but on occaſion; even in publick we may uſe our gifts, if they be grave, modeſt, diſcreet and humble; for which we have the Royal approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one, who is the beſt interpreter of the law, in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now for the Liturgy of our Church, 'tis ſuch, that Mr <hi>Fox</hi> (though a friend to the Presbyterians) ſtuck not to ſay, it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by the holy Ghoſt. Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> one of our firſt Reformers, and a chief compiler there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made challenge to defend it, and to prove it perfectly agreeable to the word of God, and the ſame in effect which had been 1500 years in the Church of Chriſt;<note place="margin">B. <hi>Gauden.</hi>
               </note> and ſaith a late Reverend Writer, Let any ſober man, that is able, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> with thoſe now extant, and he will finde nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in any of them, but is in this of our Church; many things which are leſs clear or neceſſary in them are better expreſt or wiſely omitted in this: Neither is there (ſaith another) any ancient claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically condemned hereſy to be found in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Councils, Church-hiſtories, confutation of Fathers, which is not by ſome clauſe or other of our common-prayer excluded; nor could all its moſt ſpiteful adverſaries ever yet draw up any material objection againſt it, but have ſtill diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered more weakneſs in themſelves then in that.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53310:16"/>But laſtly, whilſt we are ſpeaking of prayer, let us minde the houſe of prayer: that there have ever been in the Church of God places conſecrated and ſet apart for his worſhip, whereto all were bound to reſort. I might here aſcend up as high as <hi>Adam,</hi> and bring this cuſtome down to our preſent age, and ſhew you, how that before the fall in Paradiſe God had that which was analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical to a Church or Temple, a diſtinct place where he manifeſted himſelf in a peculiar and ſpecial manner,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8. Vid. <hi>Talmud. Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>achi.</hi>
               </note> for ſo the phraſe <hi>Mippene Jehovah</hi> is underſtood by the Jews; accordingly not long after, <hi>Cain</hi> for murder is ſaid to be baniſhed from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.16. and <hi>Abel</hi> though he ſacrificed abroad and in an open place, yet it ſeems it was in a place prepared or ſet apart for that purpoſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. but I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf to ſpeak only to the time of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the next ſucceeding Ages, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Gentile Court of the Temple, which our Saviour declared to be a place conſecrated by virtue of that Text of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> 'tis well known how that our Saviour and his Apoſtles often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired for the publick exerciſe of Religion to the Jewiſh Synagogues and Temple; beſides here were then other places of prayer ſet apart by the Jews, and frequented by the Chriſtians, nay by Chriſt himſelf, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.12. and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all night, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>Gods houſe of prayer;</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>a houſe of prayer,</hi> as well as <hi>prayer</hi> it ſelf: in which ſence <hi>Juvenal</hi> uſeth the words <hi>In quâ te quaero Proſeu cha,</hi> and it muſt be ſo underſtood here, or elſe there cannot well be any true gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53310:16"/>
conſtruction made of the words without wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or at leaſt ſtreightning the ſence:<note place="margin">Vid. Tremel. in locum.</note> ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 16.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where <hi>a houſe of prayer</hi> was famed or reputed to be the Arabick <hi>locus orationis;</hi> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack <hi>domus orationis,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> made it a place to preach in alſo: we have the ſame word again in the 16th. <hi>verſe;</hi> and in the like manner may we render it, as we went <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to a houſe of prayer a Damſell met us; nay, their going from one place to another to pray, doth argue as much, <hi>viz.</hi> that they had then ſome places more peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar for prayer then others. Chriſt and his Apoſtles found other conſecrated places which they made uſe of for publick and Divine Service; ſuch were the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or upper Rooms ſo often mentioned in the Old and New Teſtament, which as the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Gregory</hi> obſerves in his critical Notes, were no other then places ſet apart for prayer and other religious exerciſes: now 'tis certain, that Chriſt and his Apoſtles repaired not to theſe places in compliance with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rites, or becauſe of any command in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s law, but that they might perform their Chriſtian Solemnities in places hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or fit for ſuch ſacred uſes; and it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Apoſtles themſelves in ſome ſhort proceſs of time, or ſome other convert Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as were contemporary with them, did deſtinate and ſet apart houſes of their own, which after Dedication for diſtinction ſake (as they called the Chriſtian-Sabbath the Lords day ſo) they called theſe Chriſtian Synagogues, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Churches, and in ſome time after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay, the Lords: from whence the the Engliſh work <hi>Kurk,</hi> or with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53310:17"/>
an aſpirate, Church, which is as much as to ſay, the Lords; now that 'tis very likely, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did conſecrate and ſet apart ſuch houſes of their own, even in the Apoſtles time, appears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we finde the Apoſtle mentioning ſome ſuch place or places diſtinguiſhed by name from any as were in uſe among the Jews, as is evident from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.28, 35. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 20. this is made yet more probable from Inſtances out of ancient hiſtory, which ſpeaks of many Churches even in the Apoſtles times: St. <hi>Martialis</hi> who lived near their time,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ. <hi>Chap. 8.</hi>
               </note> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch religious ſtructures then already in uſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cat. Epiſt.</hi> 5.8.</note> the like doth <hi>Niceph. Conſtantipolitanus;</hi> and he inſtances in one among the reſt founded by St. <hi>Andrew.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. vit. <hi>St.</hi> Luk. Catch. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Simeon Metaphraſtes</hi> tells of Temples and Altars built by St. <hi>Luke;</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaith, that that place was a Church conſecrated by the Apoſtles, in which they were aſſembled at the day of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt:</hi> ſome likewiſe think, that the houſe in which the bleſſed Virgin Mother dwelt at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> was made a Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Turſel. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Annal. Vid</hi> l. 8. c. 1. and <hi>lib.</hi> 4. c. 45.</note> and conſecrated by the Apoſtles: and <hi>Alexander</hi> reports in the life of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> that St. <hi>Marks</hi> houſe <hi>Act.</hi> 12.12. was a Chriſtian Temple or Oratory, probably ſuch an one as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for ſuch the Primitive Chriſtians had in imitation of the Jews, and St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> mentions a famous Church there: <hi>Euſebius</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpeaks of Oratories and Churches which he calls <hi>priſca Aedificia,</hi> which denotes they were of ſome hundred years ſtanding, otherwiſe they could not be well termed old or ancient; and therefore they were ſuch doubtleſs as were built in the Apoſtles
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53310:17"/>
times: but if we look to the Ages immediately ſucceeding the Apoſtles, even to the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> and lower, I need not deſcend: we cannot want Inſtances to prove, that there were houſes conſecrated and ſet apart by Chriſtians themſelves, and that they had every where Oratories and Churches of their own, which they made uſe of for their Religious ſolemnities. <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew ſpeaking of the worſhippers of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 2. 17</note> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very village they had a Religious houſe which they call <hi>Seminon,</hi> which comes near the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies a place of worſhip: and if <hi>Lucian</hi> may be believed,<note place="margin">Dial Philoſ.</note> he deſcribes one of the Chriſtian Churches richly guilt and adorned in <hi>Trajans</hi> time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat.</hi> l. 2. c. 8.</note> who lived <hi>Anno</hi> 103. nor is it but to be admired how zealous the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a houſe of prayer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zozomon.</hi> l. 3. c. 5.</note> who as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Zozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tell us, built many himſelf, and ſuch as were very magnificent;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. de Vit. Conſt.</hi> lib. 4. c. 56. <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 1. c. 14.</note> and being about to make war with the <hi>Perſians,</hi> he cauſed a Tabernacle or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Temple to be made, to carry with him, that therefore he might always have a holy houſe for his God, ſanctified and prepared for religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And now as it hath been thus the cuſtome in all Ages to have places ſet apart for prayer and other religious Rites, ſo there have been Laws and Conſtitutions made, as now at this day in our Church, to enjoyn the people to repair thereunto: 'twas made a law in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the Tribes ſhould go up to the Temple, and conſonant thereto is <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Injunction in the firſt times of the Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all to one place, all to the Temple of God, in his undoubted Epiſtle
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53310:18"/>
reaſon of the firſt building or erecting of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, <hi>Non ut diviſi ſimus cum convenire oportet, ſed ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſi conjungamur, q. d.</hi> to prevent Conventicles and ſuch like clandeſtine factious meetings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, calls them</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis docet do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Deicon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptibile in eſſe &amp; conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tusqui in ce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athmaſit. <hi>Cannon. 5.</hi> Canon. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> and ſuch like the Law of our Land accounts all religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aſſemblies in private houſes and places un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed and common; for which cauſe <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperour enacted a Law againſt them, and the ancient Council of <hi>Gangra</hi> held in the purer times of the Church about the year 324. pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and his adherents, who held that Churches ſhould be neglected, and publick meetings in them left off, and that there ſhould be no other Churches but mens private houſes, and no other meetings but Conventicles: Even in heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> the moſt learned <hi>P. Aerodius</hi> tells us when a ſort of Innovatours kept their Conventicles in oppoſition to the way received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, of worſhipping their Gods, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate made an Act there ſhould be no ſuch meeting, as tending to the diſturbance of the State and the publick peace; <hi>Et ſi quis tale ſacrum ſolemne &amp; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium duceret:</hi> and the Senate gave him leave, it muſt be with this condition, that when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his offices of Religion his own way, <hi>ita id ſacrum faceret dum ne plures quam quinque ſacrificio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſent;</hi> and if they were thus ſollicitous to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and eſtabliſh, as a ſacred inviolable thing, the Idolatrous worſhip of their falſe Gods, what care can be great enough to ſecure the ſolemn worſhip of the only true God, when it is ſhaken by ſuch diviſions? moreover in the days of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, there was a Cannon made in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53310:18"/>
of <hi>Towers,</hi> wherein the people were required to behave themſelves reverently in the Church, to which our 18. Canon well agrees, and both to that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. but this by the way: ſince then we have every where Churches erected and places of publick worſhip, which we are ſtrictly enjoyned by authority to frequent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair unto, at all ſet times, and ſeaſons; what is it leſs then ſchiſm, were there nothing elſe in it, out of contempt and oppoſition to that Communion, to have recourſe to private and clandeſtine meetings; and though Antiquity mentions unto us private meetings, yet we may finde that they were not ſet up for a ſeparation, or out of opinion that better ſervices were performed there then in the Church, but they were neceſſitated thereunto by reaſon of perſecution, which oft-times lay ſore on the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, otherwiſe they brought upon them the guilt of Schiſm, and were accordingly ſo cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and held as Schiſmaticks. Thus were the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> reputed, whoſe Schiſm lay only in their Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from the appointed place of worſhip, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up another in oppoſition to it: for if we audit an account of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> guilt according to <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Joſephus, Scaliger,</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Audeam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere (<hi>ſaith</hi> Scaliger) eos adeo ab omni idololatria ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrere ut in hac parte Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daos ipſos ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare, John. <hi>8.48.</hi>
               </note> we ſhall finde they came at laſt to differ nothing from the Jews but the place of meeting; but whether this be ſuch a guilt as ſhould make thoſe terms equivalent, <hi>he is a Samaritan,</hi> he hath a devil, and is <hi>mad:</hi> I ſhall not ſay but it is ſuch as makes our Saviour ſay ſome-what excluſively, <hi>John.</hi> 4.22. all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and Salvations of the law did indeed hover upon Mount <hi>Gerizem</hi> were given thence, that was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53310:19"/>
the place of them, but they were cut away when Schiſm came; the Church is not a place of bleſſing when it is built againſt a Church, <hi>Gerizim</hi> is <hi>Ebal</hi> when it ſtands in competition with <hi>Mount Sion.</hi> Thus I have in ſome meaſure I hope, juſtifyed the Rites and Ceremonies, and Conſtitutions of our Church, by ſhewing how perfectly conformable they are to the cuſtomes of the Churches of God.</p>
            <p>All that I have now to adde is a ſhort <hi>Paraeneſis</hi> or Exhortation, that you would all be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a compleat conformity, and for you my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren of the Clergy, as we are ſet over, ſo we ſhould be both teachers and leaders of the people, both by doctrine and example, bringing them into theſe paths of religious worſhip, and directing them to walk orderly therein: as <hi>the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge,</hi> ſo we ſhould enable our ſelves not only to ſhew,<note place="margin">In <hi>France</hi> ſuch who were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with cure of ſouls were obliged to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain times to the Biſhop, whether the Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of that Church co which they were ſubject, were obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Fran. Synod. Capit.</hi> lib 5. c. 2.</note> but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the lawfulneſs of our Churches Rites and cuſtomes, and of that good old way which our Fathers walked in, whoſe ſteps we follow; this the 8 Canon enjoyns us all, to preach up twice a year at the leaſt, upon penalty of ſuſpenſation; but becauſe moſt of us, if not all, ſhall amongſt our people finde ſome, who will hate, or at leaſt, diſlike us, if we plainly tell them a truth that thwarts their prejudices, we ſhould therefore prudently inſinuate theſe things, and by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Lenocinium</hi> ſteal their affections into all the paths of truth. I cannot ſee how it is conſiſtent with our duty to conceal any part or circumſtance of religious worſhip which hath ſo immediate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendence and reference to practice; much leſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53310:19"/>
ſhould we tread in the ſteps of thoſe in a ſence worſe then non-conforming Brethren, who to gain the affections of the giddy and injudicious, and make their lower parts ſeem tall and reverend, diſcover a diſlike to ſome of the Churches Rites and Ceremonies, whereby others are traduced by the male-contented party, (who brook every man the better by how much the leſs obedient) for perſons more ſuperſtitious (as they call it) then they need, by which means alſo they work a kinde of averſion in thoſe who were in a fair way to be perfectly conformable, and confirm ſuch who have already forſaken our Communion; let us then above all others take heed we do not by this means enhanſe the repute of a faction, nor let us encourage a peeviſh Schiſmatick by Chriſtening his childe without the Croſs or Surplice; to abate the Croſs or Ring, to lay aſide the Surplice, to curtail the prayers, to omit the Letany or ſecond ſervice, I know recommends a man farther to ſome humours, then all the parts, learning and ſobriety of another that is faithful to his duty; but I beſeech all to remember that it is God and conſcience, and the publick laws that ought to be ſatisfied, and not a private intereſt or a faction. You have all taken the Oaths of Supremacy and Canonical obedience, and there is nothing required of you but what the King may lawfully command, nothing but what the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church enjoyn, and what your ſelves when you entred into the Miniſtry knew you were all bound to obſerve; but if there be any that will not conſider and weigh there Engagements, I hope the reſpective Church-wardens will look to their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53310:20"/>
Oath, and make a true Preſentment, not forſwear themſelves to excuſe their Miniſters; and methinks none can take it ill, if they will not hazard thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſouls which themſelves labour to ſave: the like care ought the Church-wardens to take in preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faults and faileurs of the people as well as of their Miniſter, as by Oath they are bound, which in caſe you wilfully omit, the 117 Canon declares, the Ordinary may proceed againſt you in ſuch ſort, as in cauſes of wilfull perjury in a Court Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal 'tis already by Law provided; but if the Church-wardens do conſcientiouſly diſcharge their duty, and delinquents be duly preſented, and then they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue perverſe and refractory, and ſo prove contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they are in the next place to be rejected and cenſured as Impugners of the Cuſtomes of the Church, according to that of our Apoſtle in the text: <hi>If any ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53310:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
